Inventory to the J. C. Hurewitz papers
Hoover Institution Archives
J.C. Hurewitz papers
1789-2005
88012
Hoover Institution Archives
107 manuscript boxes, 1 card file box, 6 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder (45.4 linear feet)
The J. C. Hurewitz papers consisted originally of a collection of printed materials, much of it relating to the history of the British mandate of Palestine. This part (Boxes 1-22) includes numerous publications issued by various Zionist parties in the period leading up to the creation of the state of Israel. The increment to the papers greatly expands the volume of the collection, making it a significant addition to the holdings of the archives on the history and politics of the Middle East. The incremental materials reflect Hurewitz's professional involvement with the region over a period of more than fifty years, beginning as a U.S. government analyst and then continuing during a long and distinguished academic career as a professor of political science at Columbia University. The increment consists of speeches and writings; a subject file of clippings, articles, and reports; correspondence and conference materials; photocopies of documents; and printed matter.
Hurewitz, J. C.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1998, with an increment in 2012
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1914 Born, Hartford, Connecticut
1936 B.A., Trinity College
1937 M.A., Columbia University
1943-1945 Senior political analyst, Office of Strategic Services
1946 Political adviser to the U.S. Cabinet Committee on Palestine
1949-1950 Political affairs officer, UN Secretariat
1950 Author, The Struggle for Palestine
1950 Ph.D., Columbia University
1950-1984 Professor of government, Columbia University
1953 Author, Middle East Dilemmas
1956 Author, Diplomacy in the Near and Middle East: A Documentary Record
1969 Author, Middle East Politics: The Military Dimension
1974 Author, Middle East and North Africa in World Politics: A Documentary Record
1979 Author, The Persian Gulf: After Iran's Revolution
2008 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The J. C. Hurewitz papers consisted originally of a collection of printed materials, much of it relating to the history of the British mandate of Palestine. This part (Boxes 1-22) includes numerous publications issued by various Zionist parties in the period leading up to the creation of the state of Israel. The increment to the papers greatly expands the volume of the collection, making it a significant addition to the holdings of the archives on the history and politics of the Middle East. The incremental materials reflect Hurewitz's professional involvement with the region over a period of more than fifty years, beginning as a U.S. government analyst and then continuing during a long and distinguished academic career as a professor of political science at Columbia University. The increment consists of speeches and writings; a subject file of clippings, articles, and reports; correspondence and conference materials; photocopies of documents; and printed matter.
Hurewitz was a prolific writer, and the increment contains drafts of his major works, including volumes he edited. It includes drafts of an unpublished third volume of his The Middle East and North Africa in World Politics: A Documentary Record, as well as multiple drafts of another unpublished work, "The Tangled Web: The Struggle for the Mandate's Succession." The increment also contains numerous scholarly articles written by Hurewitz for various journals, as well as more topical articles written for magazines and newspapers. The initial focus of Hurewitz's research was on the history of the British mandate of Palestine, but he wrote on many other subjects relating to the Middle East and North Africa, ranging from Ottoman era diplomacy to the various attempts to negotiate a peace settlement between Israel and the Palestinians.
The extensive subject file in the increment largely follows Hurewitz's original arrangement and headings, and consists principally of clippings, articles, and reports. It includes detailed information on the history of the British mandate of Palestine and the complicated series of events leading up to the partition of Palestine and the founding of the state of Israel. Additionally, there are numerous materials relating to the Suez Crisis of 1956, the Algerian war of independence, the 1967 and 1973 Arab-Israeli wars, and the series of negotiations between Israel and the Palestinians in recent decades. There are accounts of the many issues involved in these negotiations, including the status of Jerusalem and the general question of Palestinian sovereignty. There are other materials describing the Israeli political landscape and the tension between religious and secular forces in the country. The subject file also documents the role played by the United States in the Middle East from the aftermath of World War II until the Iraq War.
Materials in the increment relating to Hurewitz's teaching career can be found under the headings for academic career file. These include correspondence, conference papers, and summaries of meetings held by Hurewitz with officials and academics during his trips to the Middle East and elsewhere. There are also copies of a number of lectures on Middle East history, notes for other lectures given by Hurewitz, and records kept of his various research trips.
Hurewitz's interest in the diplomatic history of the Middle East led him to acquire a large number of monographs and pamphlets devoted to this subject. The printed matter in the increment includes numerous British government publications relating to mandatory Palestine and copies of both American and British treaties negotiated with countries of the Middle East. The increment also contains many photocopies of British government documents from the Public Records Office, as well as some declassified U.S. government documents. All these relate to British and American policies in the Middle East, and include reports on various countries in the region.
Arrangement
The collection is not arranged into series.
Africa, North--History.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Middle East.; Iran--History.; Israel--History.; Middle East--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Middle East--Foreign relations--United States.; Middle East--History--20th century.; Palestine--History--1917-1948.; Suez Canal (Egypt); United States--Foreign relations--Middle East.
- Afghanistan
  - Legislation, 1931-1957
    - Texts of statutes (Box-folder 1: 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      54 booklets (in Farsi).
    - Translations (English) (Box-folder 1: 2-3)
    - Reports by U.S. Foreign Operations Administration, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 1: 4)
      23 items (processed).
    - Arab League of States (Box-folder 2: 1)
      Material in Arabic (including 5 pamphlets).
- Egypt
  - Education. Reports and memoranda, 1951-1953 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    10 items (processed).
  - Embassy Reference Library. List (Box-folder 2: 3)
    1 item (processed).
  - Land Reform Law, 1952 September (Box-folder 2: 4)
    Translation (English)
- Iran
  - Reports and charts by U.S. Foreign Operations Administration, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    25 items (processed).
  - Treaty series (Box-folder 2: 6)
    Material in Farsi. 15 items.
- Iraq. Correspondence Relating to Assyrian Settlement from 13th July 1932 to 5th August 1933. Booklet printed by Government of Iraq (Box-folder 2: 7)
- Israel/Palestine
  - Agudas Israel World Organization. Memoranda and conference reports, 1941-1946 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    Includes Isaac Breuer, "Judaism and National Home" (mainly processed).
  - Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry
    - Arab evidence, 1946 (Box-folder 3: 2)
      Processed.
    - Statement to Committee by Ihud (Union) Association of Palestine, 1946 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Archives. Legal agreement and pamphlet, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    In Hebrew (processed).
  - Irgun Zvai Leumi (National Military Organisation). "The Hebrew Struggle for National Liberation,", 1947 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Mizrachi Organizations. Pamphlets and leaflets, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    9 items.
  - Press releases of Israeli Office of Information and Embassy in U.S., 1949-1960 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    1 folder.
  - Lebanon. "The Economic Development of Lebanon,", 1948 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    Photographic reproduction of report by Sir Alexander Gibb and Partners.
  - Pakistan. Administrative reports and leaflets relating to archives, 1951-1953 (Box-folder 4: 5)
- Turkey
  - Agriculture. Reports by U.S. Foreign Operations Administration, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    4 items (processed).
  - Foreign investment and petroleum laws. Translations (English), 1953-1954 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    2 items (processed).
  - Problems of Research in Turkey, Conference on. Report, 1953 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Public administration. Reports, speech, interview, 1954 (Box-folder 4: 9)
- Microfilm of diplomatic records from Turkish national archives, circa 1789-1914 (Box 5)
  9 reels.
- Palestine
  - American Council for Judaism publications, 1944-1945, undated (Box-folder 6: 1)
    Palestine: Haven of Refuge or Power Politics, 1944; The American of Jewish Faith, 1945; The Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry, undated.
  - American Jewish Committee publications, 1943, undated (Box-folder 6: 2)
    Jewish Post-War Problems: Palestine in the New World, 1943; Eugene M. Kulischer, Jewish Migrations: Past Experiences and Post-War Prospects, 1943; Joseph M. Proskauer, In Peace and Dignity, 1946; leaflet, undated.
  - American Palestine Committee publications, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    Albert Einstein and Eric Kahler, The Arabs and Palestine, 1944; Victor Gollancz, Nowhere to Lay Their Heads, 1945; Wendell Phillips, Before the Bar of History, 1945; Dorothy Thompson, Let the Promise Be Fulfilled, 1946.
  - Avukah (American Student Zionist Federation) publications, 1936, 1939, 1942 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    Louis D. Brandeis, Call to the Educated Jew, 1936; Meir Yaari, Analysis of Zionism, 1936; Shoshanna Harris Sankowsky, Short History of Zionism, 1936, and revised edition, 1939; Relations of Jews and Arabs, 1942.
  - British government publications, 1939, 1947, 1949 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    Report of the British Guiana Refugee Commission to the Advisory Committee on Political Refugees Appointed by the President of the United States of America and Appendices, 1939; Britain and Palestine, 1947; The Political History of Palestine under British Administration, 1947; Ernest Bevin, "Palestine," 1949.
  - Habonim (Labor Zionist Youth) publications, 1945 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    David Ben Gurion, The A.B.C. of Zionist Policy, 1945; Furrows issue, 1945; Anna E. Hartog, The Jewish Communal Settlements in Palestine, 1945.
  - Hadassah (Women's Zionist Organization of America) publications, 1938, 1943, undated (Box-folder 6: 7)
    Abraham Revusky, Social Forces in Palestine, 1938; Abraham Tulin, Analysis of British Policy in Palestine, 1943; Bernard D. Weinryb, The Yishuv in Palestine, undated.
  - Hashomer Hatzair publications, 1929, 1939, 1944, 1946, undated (Box-folder 6: 8-9)
    "Zionism and the Arab Question," 1929; Lotta Levensohn, Hashomer, 1939; Mordekhay Orenstein, Palestine: A Plea for Jewish-Arab Unity, 1939; Y. Chazan, Thirty Years of Hashomer Hatzair, 1944; Pioneer Saga: The Story of Hashomer Hatzair, 1944; The Case for a Bi-National Palestine, 1946; Hashomer issue, 1946; Hedim issue, 1946; Ve'idat ha-yesod, Hefah, kaf-alef-kaf-bet Adar A', Iashav, 1946; Me'ir Ya'ari, 'Im hakamat Mifleger Po'alim ha-shomer ha-Tsa'ir, 1946; broadside, undated; Darkah shel ha-Tenu'ah, undated.
  - Ihud (Union) Association publications, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    Martin Buber, Judah L. Magnes and Moses Smilansky, Palestine: A Bi-National State, 1946; M. Buber, J. L. Magnes and E. Simon, ed., Towards Union in Palestine, 1947.
  - Institute of Arab American Affairs publications, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 7: 2)
    Papers on Palestine, 1945; Arab Progress in Palestine, 1946; Arabic-Speaking Americans, 1946; Jabir Shibli, The Palestine Reality, 1946.
  - Jewish Agency for Palestine publications, 1930, 1936-1939, 1945-1947, 1950 (Box-folder 7: 3-5)
    Leonard Stein, Memorandum: The Palestine White Paper of October 1930, 1930; The Historical Connection of the Jewish People with Palestine, 1936; Report to the XXth Zionist Congress and to the Council of the Jewish Agency in Zurich, 1937; Housing in Jewish Palestine, 1938; Documents Relating to the Balfour Declaration and the Palestine Mandate, 1939; Documents Relating to the McMahon Letters, 1939; Leonard Stein, Promises and Afterthoughts, 1939; Child and Youth Aliyah, 1945; Memorandum Submitted to the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry on Palestine, 1946; Political Report of the London Office of the Executive of the Jewish Agency, 1946; Zionism and the Arab World, 1946; Observations on the Supplementary Memorandum by the Government of Palestine, 1947; The Palestine Issue, 1947; Political Survey, 1946-1947, 1947; Reply to the Government of Palestine's Memorandum on the Administration of Palestine under the Mandate, 1947; Some Legal Aspects of the Jewish Case, 1947; Zionism and the Arab World, 1947; Nahum Goldmann, The New Partnership: Zionism and the State, 1950.
  - Keren Kayemeth Leisrael (Jewish National Fund) and Keren Hayesod (Palestine Foundation Fund) publications, 1937-1940, 1947 (Box-folder 8: 1-2)
    Jacob A. Arikha, Restoration of Place-Names in Eretz Israel, 1937; Handbook of the Jewish Communal Villages in Palestine, 1938, 1938; Alex Bein, Introduction au Sionisme, 1939; Adolf Boehm and Adolf Pollak, The Jewish National Fund (Kerem Kayemeth Leisrael), 1939; Hugo Herrmann, Keren Hayesod, 1939; Jewish Jerusalem: Past and Present, 1939; Report of the Head Office /Keren Hayesod/, 1939; A. Ulitzur, Two Decades of Keren Hayesod, 1940; Eretz Israel: Facts and Figures, 1947.
  - Maps, 1924-1945 (Box-folder 8: 3)
    4 maps.
  - Masada (Youth Zionist Organization of America) publications, 1935, 1939 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    Leo Pinsker, Auto-Emancipation, 1935 and 1939 reprint.
  - Miscellaneous American Zionist/Jewish publications, 1934, 1937, 1942-1947, 1952 (Box-folder 8: 5)
    Louis D. Brandeis, The Jewish Problem, 1934; Memorandum Submitted to the Palestine Royal Commission on American Interest in the Administration of the Palestine Mandate, 1937; David Ben-Gurion, Test of Fulfillment: Can Zionism Be Achieved?, 1942; Rabbi Julian Morgenstern, Nation, People, Religion: What Are We?, 1943; Bernard D. Weinryb "Economic and Social Forms in Palestine," 1944, Ernest Frankenstein, An Open Letter to the Right Honorable Ernest Bevin, M.P., 1945; Chaim Weizmann, We Do Not Want to Return to the Past, 1945; The Jewish State in Palestine, 1947; Memorandum on Aid to the Near East, 1952; What is Hechalutz?, undated; Pierre Van Paassen, The Battle for Jerusalem, undated.
  - Miscellaneous Arab publications, 1943, 1947, undated (Box-folder 8: 6)
    Arab Bank, Jerusalem, Fourteenth Annual Report, 1943; M. Fadhel Jamali, Iraq's Point of View on the Palestine Question, 1947; Palestine: The Solution: The Arab Proposals and the Case on which They Rest, 1947; The Constitution and By-Laws of the Arab National League, undated; Bayan al-Jami'ah al-'Arabiyah, undated.
  - Miscellaneous Christian/missionary publications, 1909-1944 (Box-folder 8: 7-8)
    Includes publications of the Christian and Missionary Alliance, Newman School of Missions, Board of Foreign Missions of the Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A., American Colony Aid Association, Young Men's Christian Associations, American Friends Board of Foreign Missions, Syrisches Waisenhaus, Federal Council of the Churches of Christ In America, the Committee on Work Among Moslems.
  - Miscellaneous Palestinian Zionist/Jewish publications, 1930-1932, 1939-1940, 1946 (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
    Bernard Joseph, The White Paper on Palestine: A Criticism, 1930; Levi Gintsburg, Mekomah shel ha-halakhah be-hokhmat Yisrael, 1931/1932; Chayim Nachman Bialik, Divre Byalik 'al ha-Universitah ha-'Ivrit, 1939/1940; Darkhenu issue, 1939; Din ve-heshbon shel ha-Va'ad, mi-shenat ha-Tartsaz, 1939/40; Binyamin Peterzeyl and Ya'akov Peterzeyl, ed., Neged ha-teror: kuntres, 1939; Be-terem issue, 1946; Eliyahu Duvkin, ha-'Aliyah veha-hatsalah bi-shenot ha-Sho'ah, n.d.; Heyl Pashut, Aharon Aharonson, undated; B. Weinryb, The Second Generation in Rehovoth and its Occupational Status, undated.
  - Miscellaneous publications, 1930, 1936, 1944, 1947, 1964 (Box-folder 9: 3-4)
    Horace B. Samuel, Beneath the Whitewash, 1930; Nevill Barbour, A Plan for Lasting Peace in Palestine, 1936; T. Canaan, The Palestine Arab Cause, 1936; Solomon Yahuda, The Proposed Legislative Council and the Mandate for Palestine, 1936; al-Mukhtar issue, 1944; The Palestine Problem and Proposals for its Solution, 1947; Near East Report supplement, 1964; offprints, 1936.
  - Miscellaneous Zionist/Jewish Labor publications, 1935 (Box-folder 9: 5)
    Ber Borochov, The National Question and the Class Struggle, 1935; E. Liebenstein, The Truth about Revisionism, 1935.
  - Miscellaneous Zionist/Jewish publications, circa 1780-1880, 1934, 1936, 1943 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    Leon Simon, Synopsis on the Haskalah Movement, circa 1780-1880, Liverpool, 1934; Roit-bukh vegu di blutike gesheenishn in Palestine in yor 1936, Lodz, 1936; Round the Reconstruction Programme of the Palestine Government, Johannesburg, 1943.
  - Palestine and Middle East Magazine offprints, 1930-1945 (Box-folder 9: 7)
    3 items.
  - Palestine Economic Corporation of New York. Annual reports and prospectus on the issue of $1,500,000 common stock, 1940-1944 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Poale Zion publications, 1934, 1937-1938, 1942-1946 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    Poyle-Tsiyon in der itstiker tekufe, 1934; Berl Katznelson, Revolutionary Constructivism, 1937; 10-te Velt Konferents fun Farband Linke Poyle-Tsiyon, Detsember 1937, 1938; Berl Locker, Palestine and the Jewish Future, 1942; Ephraim Broido, Jews, Arabs and the Middle East, 1944; The Last Stand: Jewish Resistance in Nazi Europe and the Role of the Labor Zionist Movement, 1944; A. Zabarsky, The Jewish Co-operative Movement in Palestine, 1944; Z. Abramovitsh and Y. Peterzeyl, Englisher imperyalizm um Erets-Yisrael; Antisemitizm firt tsum soyf fun der Britisher imperye; Der Federatsye-plan, 1946; Undzer vort issue, Buenos Aires, 1946; Betsalel Sherman, A yidish land oder a naye geto?, undated; What is Socialist Zionism?, undated; World Labour and the Jewish People: The Jewish Case before the World Trade Union Conference, London, February 6th to 17th, 1945, undated.
  - Radio broadcast debate transcripts. University of Chicago Round Table and Town Meeting of the Air, 1945-1949 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    6 items.
  - Sinai Magazine offprints, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - United Palestine Appeal publications, 1926, 1950, undated (Box-folder 10: 4)
    Colonel Josiah C. Wedgewood, American Addresses, 1926; The Refugee Problem and the Absorptive Capacity of Palestine, undated; Dr. Joseph B. Schechtman, Exodus from Iraq, 1950.
  - United States government publications, 1922, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 10: 5)
    Addison E. Southard, Palestine: Its Commercial Resources with Particular Reference to American Trade, 1922; The Jewish National Home in Palestine, 1944; Earl G. Harrison, The Plight of the Displaced Jews in Europe, 1945; Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry, 1946; al-Hayah fi qaryah Amrikiyah, undated.
  - Zionist Organization publications, 1927, 1939, 1945, undated (Box-folder 10: 6-7)
    Beschlusse des XV Zionisten-Kongresses, 1927; Israel Cohen, The Progress of Zionism, 1939; Eliezer Liebenstein, Le nouveau territorialisme juif, 1945; Edwin Samuel, Handbook of the Jewish Communal Villages in Palestine, 1945; Alex Bein, The History of Jewish Agricultural Settlement in Palestine, undated; Lotta Levensohn, The Plain of Bethshan: Ancient and Modern, undated; Joseph Weitz, Palestine's Agricultural Potentialities, undated; Shlomo Zemach, An Introduction to the History of Labour Settlement in Palestine, undated; Dr. A. Ankorion, The Government of Palestine, 1945.
  - Zionist Organization of America publications, 1937-1938, 1944, undated (Box-folder 10: 8)
    N. William Hazen, Absorptive Capacity of Palestine: Agriculture, 1937; Abraham H. Friedland, Jewish Culture in Palestine: Literature, 1938; G. Menahem, Professor Zebi (Herman) Schapira, 1938; Deborah Pessin, Ahad Ha'am, Chaim Weizmann, Moses Hess, Nahum Sokolow, Theodor Herzl, all 1938; Why Zionism?, 1938; Carl Alpert, Palestine between Two Wars, 1944; Ira Eisenstein, The Jordan: A New Frontier of Democracy, undated; Emanuel Neumann, The Birth of Jewish Statesmanship: A Story of Theodor Herzl's Life, undated.
- Suez Canal
  - Le Canal. Two issues, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 10: 9)
  - Le Canal de Suez. Scattered issues, 1875-1914 (Box 11)
  - Compagnie Universelle du Canal Maritime de Suez. Annual reports, 1915-1940, 1945-1954 (Box 12)
- Israel/Palestine
  - Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry. Memoranda, reports, and statements, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 13: 1)
    Submitted to the Committee by the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee; the Arab Office, Jerusalem; the Intergovernmental Committee on Refugees; the Jewish Resistance Movement; the Palestine Government; the United States Department of State; the Rev. Charles T. Bridgeman; and Earl G. Harrison. 8 items (mainly processed).
  - Haganah. Leaflets, flyers, brochures, bulletins, and translations of radio broadcasts, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 13: 2)
    In Hebrew and English. 21 items (mainly processed).
  - Irgun Zvai Leumi (National Military Organisation)
    - Aims and Methodes [sic], undated (Box-folder 13: 3)
    - Fighting Judea, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 13: 4)
      5 items (mainly processed). Includes an issue of The Fighting Zion, October 1944.
    - Herut, 1945 April, 1946 February (Box-folder 13: 5)
      2 items.
    - Leaflets, flyers, and bulletins, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 13: 6)
      In Hebrew and English. 30 items (processed).
    - Memorandum distributed to all United Nations members except Britain, 1947 April-May (Box-folder 13: 7)
    - "Only Thus,", 1944 November (Box-folder 13: 8)
    - Voice of Fighting Zion radio broadcast transcripts, 1947 June-December (Box-folder 13: 9)
      28 items (mainly processed).
- Palestine
  - Government of Palestine
    - Draft ordinance on Anglo-Persian Oil Company pipeline concession, 1938 August 30 (Box-folder 13: 10)
      As reprinted in the Palestine Gazette of 1938 September 8.
    - Staff list, 1943 (Box-folder 13: 11)
  - Department of Labour
    - Annual report, 1942 (Box-folder 13: 12)
    - Bulletins, 1943 (Box-folder 13: 13)
    - Newspaper issue, 1943 November (Box-folder 13: 14)
      In Hebrew. From when the Hebrew press was banned.
  - Hadassah (Women's Zionist Organization of America). Reports prepared by the Committee for the Study of Arab-Jewish Relations, 1941 December-1943 May (Box-folder 13: 15)
    10 items.